hey everyone Professor Davis here again
to talk to you a little bit about hyper
conjugation specifically how that
applies to carbocation
stability so carbocations are most
stable when they're more substituted we
know this from our lecture
course and we also know that alkal
groups are weekly electron donating and
that's the mechanism by which they
stabilize
carbocations because reducing or
delocalizing charges in small Organics
gives those ions greater stability so we
expect methyl carbocations to be very
rare because they're so
unstable primary is not much better but
when we get on to secondary and tertiary
carbocations we see these constantly in
organic chemistry these are Staples of
first order substitution and elimination
reactions and the reason is that those
alkal groups are increasing the
stability of the
carbocation so let's take a look at what
it is about these R groups that allows
them to donate electrons or to put
electrons close to that carbocation
Center so here I've drawn for you the
methyl cation and the ethyl cation and
these two carbocations you're not really
going to see in a genuine Bonafide
reaction because they're just not stable
enough but they're the simplest examples
that will allow me to demonstrate how
hyper conjugation works so let's set
aside the fact that these are
unreasonably stable and just take a look
at them right now
anyway so I'm going to turn them into
three-dimensional representations and
then I'm going to turn these
representations on their
side and when I do this I can place the
unoccupied p orbital of each carbocation
Center vertically in the plane of our
page now what's different between the
ethyl and methyl cations is that the
ethyl cation has a neighboring CH Sigma
bonding molecular orbital and this
bonding molecular orbital is actually
filled with electrons that's how it's
holding on to the
hydrogen but we also know that these
electrons though I've drawn them here in
between the two bonded atoms we know
that they actually have free run of that
entire volume that is defined by the
molecular
orbital so they can run all around up
and down and as you notice occasionally
they find their way over to the empty p
orbital on the carbocation
and when this happens they slightly
attenuate the positive charge thereby
decreasing it and remember what we said
previously anything that decreases or
delocalizes charge in small organic
molecules or ions is going to stabilize
them so this is why having additional
alkal groups around a carbocation center
makes them more stable and therefore
more likely to
form so next time we'll talk a little
bit about how this hyper conjugate ation
and the stabilizing effect of alkal
groups on carbocations leads to things
like hydride and methyl shifts and I'll
see you then